Guide to the Baptist Church of Campbell and Bath records,1854-1890.
Baptist Church of Campbell and Bath records,1854-1890
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Baptist Church of Campbell and Bath records, 1854-1890.
6095
Baptist Church of Campbell and Bath (Savona, N.Y.)
1 reel microfilm.
Microfilm.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
One volume of annual meeting minutes (1854-1924) containing a subscription list (1874); a volume of membership records showing attendance (1866-1886) and a register of baptisms and members and covenant meeting minutes (1855-1890).
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
On November 29, 1828 members of different churches met in Hornby and agreed to draw up Articles of Faith and a Covenant for a new church. They were constituted as The Baptist Church of Hornby and Bath on June 24, 1829 having organized as a conference in December, 1828. The church changed its name to The Baptist Church of Campbell and Bath in 1832, and incorporated under that name in 1854. The church's first ordained minister began his work in 1838. On June 26, 1855 a new meeting house was dedicated.
Members from this church were given leave to form a church in Hornby and Mud Creek in the 1830's, in Oak Hill in 1849 and in Campbell in 1874. Prior to the last split the church filed a petition to change its name to the Savona Baptist Church to conform to the post office and location in Savona, a village in Bath Township.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
This collection contains one volume of annual meeting minutes (1854-1924) containing a subscription list (1874); a volume of membership records showing attendance (1866-1886) and a "Register" which includes a brief history of the church, a list of pastors, baptisms and members; and Covenant Meeting minutes, (1855-1890).
SUBJECTS
Names:
Baptist Church of Campbell and Bath (Savona, N.Y.); Baptist Church of Hornby and Bath (N.Y.)
Subjects:
Baptist associations--New York (State)--Savona.; Church records and registers--New York (State)--Savona.
Places:
Steuben County (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Campbell (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Savona (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Baptismal certificates.; Minutes (administrative records)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Trustee's Records of the Baptist Church and Society in Savona, Volume 1
  Trustee records minutes of annual meetings to elect trustees containing time, place, date, an account of notices given, the results of elections and, occasionally, resolutions concerning church property. Contents include:
  - Page 1-3
    "The Law on religious incorporation."
  - Page 4-6
    "Powers and duties of trustees."
  - 2/27/54
    First meeting to elect trustees.
  - 3/6/54
    Motion to build a meeting house.
  - 1874
    Last entry.
  - 1874
    Subscription list.
  - 1866-1876
    Expense list.
  - 1882
    "A list of Names of those who paid toward repairing the church 1882."
- Revised list of members of the Campbell and Bath Baptist Church, 1866-1886, Volume 2
  List contains names of members, if dismissed or deceased, if elected deacon and, occasionally, how received. In addition, a second list records attendance by year (1868-1890), and by month (1874-1887). The list for 1887 was not microfilmed. It can be found in the accessions folder.
- Register, Book B, 1855-1890, Volume 3
  This "register" contains a brief history of the congregation, a list of baptisms, pastors and members, and covenant meeting minutes (1855-1890). Note that the microfilm target sheet prefaces volume three inaccurately stating "#6097".
  - Page 1-4
    A Brief History of the Campbell and Bath.
  - Page 4
    List of pastors.
  - Page 5
    List of baptisms shows administrator, date and number.
  - Page 8-13
    Disposition of members, pastors and deacons.
  - Page 14-
    Covenant minutes commence. 9/8/55. Minutes name the moderator, approximate attendance, report on some disciplinary cases, and record the disposition of members. Special Covenant meetings are also recorded. Items of note include:
    June 5, 1869: Reported formation of a branch of the church in Campbell.
    January 3, 1874: Voted to apply to change the name of the church to the Savona Baptist Church. Application is granted.
    March 7, 1874: Campbell branch is set off as the First Baptist Church of Campbell.
    Mar. 7-23, 1879: Revival.
    August 2, 1890: Last meeting. "A Centennial Trustee Law" 1876. Obituaries of Jerome B. Peterson and Almira Brundage.